<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>This is written in plainnesse of heart, and bowels of everlasting love to my persecutors who have shot sore at me, and hated me without a cause. Both magistrates, priests and people in Stafford sheir, of elsewhere, that ye all may be turned from the darknesse to the light, and from anti-christ without, unto Chrust within, who is the light of the world, and hath lighted wvery man therein with his saving light. Some queres also, for such who call themselves ministers of Christ, but are altogether unlike him, or his ministers to answer. Together with a warning from the Lord God of life and power to repent, andleave persecuting, and striving against, or kicking against the Lord. Written from one who have been in the pit, death, grave, and Hell; but am come from far, and am sit down with Abraham, Isaack, and Jacob, in the heavenly places with them that are in Christ, but unknown to you, I am: but by the name I have received amongst you, Humphry Wollrich.</title>
            <author>Wollrich, Humphry, 1633?-1707.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1661</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 42 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A66862</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W3299</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R219472</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99830940</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99830940</idno>
            <idno type="VID">35402</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A66862)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 35402)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1880:20)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>This is written in plainnesse of heart, and bowels of everlasting love to my persecutors who have shot sore at me, and hated me without a cause. Both magistrates, priests and people in Stafford sheir, of elsewhere, that ye all may be turned from the darknesse to the light, and from anti-christ without, unto Chrust within, who is the light of the world, and hath lighted wvery man therein with his saving light. Some queres also, for such who call themselves ministers of Christ, but are altogether unlike him, or his ministers to answer. Together with a warning from the Lord God of life and power to repent, andleave persecuting, and striving against, or kicking against the Lord. Written from one who have been in the pit, death, grave, and Hell; but am come from far, and am sit down with Abraham, Isaack, and Jacob, in the heavenly places with them that are in Christ, but unknown to you, I am: but by the name I have received amongst you, Humphry Wollrich.</title>
                  <author>Wollrich, Humphry, 1633?-1707.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 20 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Robert Wilson, at the signe of the Black-spread-Eagle and wind-Mill in Martins-lane near Aldersgate,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1661]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place and date of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Friends' House Library, London.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Society of Friends --  Apologetic works --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Quakers --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Christian literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:35402:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>This is Written in PLAINNESSE OF HEART, and Bowels of Everlaſting love to my PERSECUTORS, WHO HAVE Shot Sore at me, and hated me without a cauſe.</p>
            <p>Both Magiſtrates, Prieſts and People in <hi>Staf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford</hi> Sheir, or elſewhere, that ye all may be turned from the Darkneſſe to the Light, and from Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt without, unto Chriſt within, who is the Light of the World, and hath lighted every man therein with his ſaving Light.</p>
            <p>Some Queres alſo, for ſuch who call them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves Miniſters of Chriſt, but are altogether unlike him, or his Miniſters to Anſwer.</p>
            <p>Together with a Warning from the Lord God of Life and Power to Repent, and leave Perſecuting, and ſtriving againſt, or kicking againſt the Lord.</p>
            <p>Written from one who have been in the Pit, Death, Grave, and Hell; But am come from Far, and am ſit down with <hi>Abraham, Iſaack,</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi> in the Heavenly places with them that are in Chriſt, but unknown to you, I am: But by the Name I received amongſt you, <hi>H<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>MPHRY WOLLRICH.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>2 Cor. 3.6.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>God hath made us able Miniſters or the New Teſtament, not of the Letter, which kills, but of the Spirit which gives Life.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>Printed for <hi>Robert Wilſon,</hi> at the ſigne of the Black-ſpread-Eagle and wind-Mill in <hi>Martins</hi>-lane near <hi>Alderſgate.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:35402:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:35402:2"/>
            <p>COme all ye Magiſtrates, Rulers and Officers in <hi>Stafford,</hi> which are ſworn to do Juſtice, and ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e Judgement, and lay the ſword upon the neck of the Wicked, and to be a terrour to Evil doers, and a ſtrength and a praiſe to them that do Well. Come all to the Light, wherewith Chriſt, who is the True Light, hath enlightned you with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, and ſo you ſhall ſee the Evil doer, deceiver and ſeducer, which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> to ſinne, iniquity, and trangreſſion, nearer you than you were aware; even he which reignes and rules in <hi>Stafford,</hi> and leads the Inhabitants thereof into Swaring, Lying, and Drunkeneſſe: ſo that your being Chriſtians is onely in words, ye being dead in your treſpaſſes and ſinnes, and the God of the World having blinded the eye by which the Lord hath ſaid he will guide, and lead his people into all Truth, out of all iniquity, tranſgreſſion, and ſinne, which the Inhabitants of <hi>Stafford</hi> abounds withall, and yet have covered themſelves with a Profeſſion, and have got the Prophets words, and Chriſts words, but are inwardly ravened, and caſt the Law of the Lord behind them, which is Light, and have reiected the Word of the Lord, which is nigh them in their hearts, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.8. And this is the Word that opens the blinde Eye, and is immortal and unchangeable, and is like a fire, and like a hammer. Sinke down and ye ſhall feel it ſo, and this is it which was before the Bible was, which your falſe Teacher tells you is the Word of the Lord, and opens the blinde Eye; and this is the Word which was before the World was, whom the Jewes, which had the Words, Slew, and Crucified; and this is falſe Doctrine: for <hi>David</hi> prayed the Lord that he would open his eyes, <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 119.18. and <hi>Pſal.</hi> 146.8. The Lord openeth the eyes of the blind, the Lord raiſeth them that are bowed down, and looſeth the bonds of the priſoner, <hi>Iſaiah.</hi> 42.6, 7. where you may read, That it is onely the work of Chriſt, to open the blinde Eyes, and to bring out the Priſoners from the priſon, and them that ſit in Darkneſſe out of the Priſon houſe: And this is he which commands the Conſciences of men which love him, and the Condemnation of all that hate him, and rebell againſt
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:35402:3"/>him, and not the Bible as your blinde Guide tells you. And why will you be ſo blinde as to look upon me as an evil Doer, who was moved of the Lord to queſtion this Doctrine, that poor ignorant people, who are in their ſinnes might be deceived no longer; and the Lord God Almighty is my witneſſe, and the teſtimony of the Lord ſtands ſure and ſhall witneſſe for me in you all, that I do not this wickedly or maliciouſly, nor in ſtubbornneſſe either againſt Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate or Miniſter, but in obedience to the Lord, and that people which lie in darkneſſe might be turned to the light, from the power of Satan unto God? and why will you call this deluſion, or a deluding Spirit, that cauſeth Drunkards to leave off their drunkeneſſe, and become ſober and temperate, and Swarers to leave their ſwaring, and Lyars to ſpeak the truth; and in the power of the Lord God, I warne you all to conſider what is my tranſgreſſion or ſinne amongſt you, for which I have been impriſoned eight or nine times in <hi>Stafford?</hi> Which of you have I cauſed, that was ſober, to become a drunkard? or what Countenancers have I been of lyars, ſwearers, and mockers there amongſt you? I ſay, Is it for any of theſe things for which I have been ſo often impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned? or have I not ſuffered for bearing a teſtimony againſt theſe things which <hi>Stafford</hi> doth abound with, notwithſtanding all their Profeſſion? And is not your Markets, which I have been moved of the Lord to ſpeak in, and to cry out againſt theſe things, yet abounding with Swearers and Drunkards, which go reeling up and down the ſtreets un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puniſhed? neither are they looked upon is deceivers, or deceived; neither are they counted a diſturbance, or trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blers of your Iſrael. And how doth your Steeple-houſes abound, and your Church made up of ſuch as theſe, which profeſſe Chriſt in words, but have loſt the Life, and are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together unlike Chriſt, or Chriſtians, and to every good word, and work, are reprobates? and by ſuch as theſe are we perſecuted, and abuſed, who have loſt both form and power of godlineſſe, and are enemies to the life of Chriſt, which they in words profeſſe; therefore the Lord God Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty hath raiſed up many witneſſe, and in his Life and
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:35402:3"/>Spirit; and by the Power of the Lord are they led to bare a teſtimony againſt all your falſe Teachers which are run, and God never ſent them; and have cryed, the Lord ſaith it unto you, when the Lord hath not ſpoken to them, but are theeves and robbers, and are climed up another way than by Chriſt, the Door: and ſo are become theeves and robbers, and have ſtolne Chriſts words, and the Apoſtles words, and are condemning the Jewes for Crucifying Chriſt, but themſelves are Crucifying him again, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſoning, perſecuting, and ſtoning them in whom he is made manifeſt and ſo are you like the Jewes, and your Prieſts have no other weapons, nor no other ſword to cut down Hereticks withall, but priſons, clubs, and ſtaffes, which are Carnall, as the High Prieſts weapons were, and not Spiritual, as <hi>Pauls</hi> was: and the Jewes which had the Prophets words, and thought to have Eternal Life therein, were Condemning their Fathers for killing the Prophets; but they would not come to Chriſt, who the Light of the World, that they might have Life, who was the end of all the Prophets, and the life of all the Prophets, him they Crucified as a Deceiver and Blaſphemer, and prince of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils: Therefore in the fear of the Lord God, I warne you all. Take heed what you doe, or how you reſiſt, and withſtand the work of the Lord, which is a marvellous work, and a wonder; and is begun among you, though you have not an Ear to hear, nor an Eye to ſee, (who are gone from the Light of the Lord in you) nor an Heart to underſtand unto this day. But why do the Heathens rage, and the People imagine a vain thing; and have ſaid in their hearts, this man ſhall not reign over them, whoſe right it is to reigne?</p>
            <p>But in vain do you ſtrive againſt your Maker, or againſt his Servant whom he ſends, who hath ſought nothing but your Souls welfare, and that you might come to know your Souls Shepherd, and be gathered into the one ſheep-fold, from all falſe Shepherds, which have lived in eaſe and pleaſure; which have eaten the fat, and clothed themſelves with the wool, but have not watched for the ſoul, as they
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:35402:4"/>that muſt give an account for them, nor cared for the ſheep, but they have been blind leaders of the blind; and they have not turned you to the Light, which is the Eye, which the god of the world hath blinded, left you ſhould ſee them to be deceivers, as they are: Read <hi>Ezek.</hi> 34.3, 4, to the 13 verſe. <hi>John</hi> 10.1. verſe to the 15.</p>
            <p>And to you, and your Teachers, who are oppoſing the work of the Lord: to you all, This is the word of the Lord God, ye are as nothing before him; and all your ſtrength is but weakneſſe, and as a tottering wall, and our Shield is departed from you; and he is riſen like a Valiant man, and his appearance is terrible as an Army with Banners; and he will Overturn, Overturn, Over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn you all, untill he reign, whoſe right it is: And the Lord God Almighty is riſen againſt all Perſecutors, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy them, and confound them, unleſſe they repent, and be warned, and agree with their Adverſary, while he is in the way: be ye wiſe, and inſtructed in love to your ſoules, I warn you all; and kiſſe the Sonne leſt he be angry, and brake you with his Iron Rod like a potters veſſell, and tear you in pieces live a Lyon, and there be none to deliver you. And I warn you all, Follow not theſe Teachers, nor own them to be your Guides, which are aſhamed to give an Anſwer of what they Preach in publick, but run away as the hireling in Chriſts time did, when they ſee him come whom they call a Wolfe. Let your Teacher, (if he be a Miniſter of Chriſt) I charge him, in the Powre of the Lord, never to preach that to the people, which he is aſhamed of before them: And before the Lord God I warn him, or any of them who preach for Hire, and ſay the Scripture is their Rule, and accuſe us for denying of it, to Anſwer theſe Queres:</p>
            <p n="1">I. Whether the Miniſters of Chriſt, who wreſtled not with Fleſh and Blood, did ever uſe Carnall weapons to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend the Truth withall? Or whether they did ever impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, or tortour the bodies of thoſe which are called. Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks, and ſo deſtroy the Handy-work of God? Or whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:35402:4"/>they which fought the Good Fight, did not uſe the Sword of the Spirit onely, which is the Word of God, and proceeds out of the mouth of the Lamb? Or, whether theſe be not your Mothers weapons, the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> which ye are crying (Whore) againſt? Come, anſwer ye Prieſts, and ye Orthodox men, and Originall men, who have loſt the true Original, and gone from the Spirit of truth, which gave forth the Scriptures, theſe Queres which are plain ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt things.</p>
            <p>Whether you have any better weapons than the High Prieſts had, which Crucified Chriſt; or the Beaſt Antichriſt, and the falſe Prophet which ye read of in the <hi>Revelations</hi> had, which made war with the Lamb and the Saints, and ſlew them which kept the teſtimony of Jeſus, and the Word of God? whether you do not fight the bad fight, as the falſe Teachers, whoſe weapons were Carnall in all Ages did; by which weapons your Church, and your Mother Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> have ſtrengthned themſelves, and do ſtrengthen themſelves to this very day? Is this to fight the Good Fight, and to wraſtle with that wicked Spirit which hath captivated the Seed, and the handy-work of God?</p>
            <p n="2">II. Whether Hebrew, Greek and Latine be the Originall, by which people muſt know the Scriptures, ſeeing they that had your Original, did Crucifie Chriſt, the true Original; and did erre, not knowing the Scriptures, nor the Power of God? Come, anſwer theſe Queres, or elſe ſtop your mouthes for ever.</p>
            <p n="3">III. Whether the Scriptures, or the Bible, be the Word of God? or, whether Chriſt be not the Word of God, which was before the Bible was? or, whether this be not the Living Word, which was as a Light, and a Lanthern to his feet; and which <hi>David</hi> hid in heart, and walked in the Light thereof, that kept him from ſinning againſt the Lord? and whether they which had the Scripture have not ſtill proved the greateſt Enemies to Chriſt? and whether he, who was the immortall, eternall, and unchangeable Word, did abide in them?</p>
            <p n="4">IV. Whether the Bible be the Rule and Guide for Saints
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:35402:5"/>to walk by, as ye preach it in your Pulpits to, be? or, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther all that are the Sonnes of God, have not in all Ages been ruled, guided, by the Spirit of God?</p>
            <p n="5">V. Come, Anſwer ye Prieſts: What is the Judge of the Spirits? whether the Bible be the Judge of the Spirits, or the Anointing which we have received from the Holy One, by which we muſt Judge, and try all things? and whether people muſt come to the Scripture, which is the Bible; or to Chriſt within, to whom all Judgement is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted?</p>
            <p n="6">VI. Whether Chriſt be the True Light that enlightneth every man? and whether, this Light, being obeyed, and followed, and taken heed too, be not ſuflicient of it ſelf to Salve man, and Redeeme man out of all ſinne and ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity; and purifie his heart, and create in man a clean heart, as God is clean, and to preſerve and keep clean in this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent evill world? Come, Anſwer all, ye deceivers, which ſay, none can be perfect in this Life: tell the people plainly by anſwering theſe Queres, whether ye are not the Children of your Mother, the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> which do believe in a Purgatory between Heaven and this Life, ſeeing you tell them they cannot be free from ſinne while they live here, and no unclean thing can enter into the Kingdome of God?</p>
            <p n="7">VII. Whether you be Miniſters of Chriſt, or Enemies to Chriſt, who are of this Belief, that none can be perfect and free from ſinne? ſeeing <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4. 11, 12. The work of the Miniſtry was for the perfecting of the Saints.</p>
            <p n="8">VIII. Whether your Preaching and Praying againſt all Sinne, be not ſinne, ſeeing ye Preach and Pray for that which you beleeve can never be? and whether all thats not of Faith, be not Sinne?</p>
            <p n="9">IX. Whether you do not make, and in effect ſay, Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan is ſtronger to keep man in Sinne, than Chriſt who came to deſtroy Sinne, and to Redeem man out of all Sinne?</p>
            <p n="10">X. Whether you do not make God a hard Task-maſter,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:35402:5"/>and charge him, wickedly, and make his commands grievous to your Hearers? ſeeing God commands men to be Holy, as he is Holy; and Pure, as he is Pure: and <hi>John</hi> ſaith his commands are not grievous.</p>
            <p n="11">XI. Whether you are not the falſe teachers that <hi>Peter</hi> ſpeaks of, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. which have forſaken Chriſt, the right way, and run greedily in the way of <hi>Balaam,</hi> after great Benefices and Rewards? and your ſelves being gone out of the way, cannot ceaſe from ſinne, and tell people they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ceaſe from ſinne alſo; and ſo all being gone out of the Councell of God, can never profit the people, but are in the ſpirit of Errour, and are clothed with the Saints words, and Sheeps clothing, but are inwardly ravened, and erred in your hearts from the Spirit of the Lord: And whether ſuch who hear you, and learn of you, are not they which are ever learning, and never able to come to the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the Truth, which is Chriſt; which he thats in ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth not.</p>
            <p n="12">XII. Whether the knowledge of ſin comes by the Bible to any man? or, what that Law was which <hi>Paul</hi> came to the knowledge of ſinne by, ſeeing, he had the Letter, while he was alive without this Law?</p>
            <p n="13">XIII. Whether Revelation be now ceaſed with any but ſuch as ye are, which are in the way of <hi>Balaam,</hi> and gone from the ſpirit by which the things of God are reveal'd? Anſwer this, ye falſe teachers that ſay Revelation is ceaſed, and that the voice of Chriſt is not heard but in the Letter of the Scripture: ſeeing the Letter ſaith, <hi>John</hi> 10. My ſheep hear my voice. And they that had the Scriptures had neither heard his Voice, nor ſeen his ſhape at any time.</p>
            <p n="14">XIV. Whether any can come to the knowledge of ſinne, but by the light within? and whether this Light be not able of it ſelf alone, to bring man to the knowledge of God? and whether, by any other thing but by the light which ſhines in the heart, man doth come to the knowledge of God? and whether this be ſufficient alone to Save man, and, redeem him out of all ſinne in this life, and keep him pure, as Chriſt is pure?</p>
            <p n="15">
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:35402:6"/> XV. Whether the Bible doth open the blind eye, ſeeing the Bible ſaith, Chriſt was ſent to open the blind eyes? whether the Bible doth command the Conſcience of man, as <hi>Noah Bryan</hi> did affirme in your Idoll Temple at <hi>Stafford?</hi> or, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Light of Chriſt in the Conſcience doth not exerciſe and command the Conſience?</p>
            <p n="16">XVI. What is the Law ſpoken of, <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 8. and the Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony? whether it be the Bible? Come, anſwer what it is, and where it is? whether it be a thing without, or within man?</p>
            <p n="17">XVII. Where is that Righteouſneſſe by which man is Juſtifed? Is it within man, and in his heart? or, was it Chriſts Righteoſnneſſe at <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> onely, which ſulfilled the Law? or, whether the Righteouſneſſe of the Law muſt not be fulfilled in man in this generation?</p>
            <p n="18">XVIII. Whether Chriſt were not the ſame before the World, or Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> was, as he was in the dayes of the Jewes; and his body the ſame which deſcended, with that which aſcended? and whether any other body did aſcend into Heaven, but the body which is Spiritual, and the only begotten of the Spirit, and was never ſeen with any carnall Eye?</p>
            <p>Comme all ye Prieſts, and you which call your ſelves Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of Chriſt, do not think to hide your ſelves any longer, or ſave your ſelves in this day of the Lords mighty power, by perſecuting and impriſoning us whom the Lord God hath raiſed up to bear a teſtimony againſt you all: and this is not your way to ſave your ſelves from the overflowing ſcourge that is coming upon you all: Butt come down to the Light of Chriſt in you, and honeſtly conſider, and ye ſhall ſee, and confeſſe that ye are not Miniſters of Chriſt, neither do ye ſpeak as the Spirit gives you utterance; neither are you Miniſters of the Spirit as they were, but of the Letter which Kills.</p>
            <p>If this be confeſſed, and owned amongſt you, then you need not anſwer theſe Queres: But if you will not confeſſe to the Lord, and owne your ſhame, and all your Worſhips
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:35402:6"/>which is taught you but by the precepts of men then anſwer theſe which follow:</p>
            <list>
               <item>I. Where did the Miniſters of Chriſt hire them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves for ſo much a year, or make a bargain with the people, either for leſſe or more? or, whether their Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry was not freely given them of the Lord? and whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they were not freely to give it others? or, whether that be Gods gift which ye buy at <hi>Oxford</hi> for ſo much Money, and learn in ſo long a time, and ſell it again in the Country for ſo much by the hour glaſſe?</item>
               <item>II. Whether the Miniſters of Chriſt, who were led by the Spirit of Chriſt, which was never limited by an hour glaſſe? whether they, did ſtudy in the week day, or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent, or ſpeak a divination of their own brain to the the people, when they were met together? or, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they did not ſpeak as the Spirit gave them utte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance?</item>
               <item>Again, where did the Miniſters of Chriſt teach people to ſing <hi>Davids</hi> Pſalmes with another heart than <hi>David</hi> had? or give <hi>Davids</hi> Pſalmes to a company of mockers, ſcorners, and perſecutors? and whether <hi>David</hi> be not made the Song of the Drunkards by you now as ever he was?</item>
               <item>III. Where did the Miniſters of Chriſt ever ſprinkle Infants, and tell poor ignorant people it was an Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of God? You which ſay the Scripture is your Rule, Anſwer, and ſhew ſome Scipture for theſe things.</item>
               <item>IV. Where do you ever read, That the Miniſters of Chriſt did ever impriſon, perſecute or ſue any man for filthy lucre as ye do.</item>
               <item>IV. Where do you ever read, That the Miniſters of Chriſt did ever impriſon, perſecute, or ſue any man for filthy lucre as ye do.</item>
               <item>V. Whether you are not thoſe falſe Teachers, and anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſts, and falſe Chriſts which Chriſt, <hi>Mat.</hi> 24. ſaid ſhould come in the laſt times; and <hi>John,</hi> who as one of his Apoſtles, in his Epiſtle ſaid were come already? and whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>John</hi> was not in the Light, and they went out from him in the way of <hi>Balaam,</hi> and for filthy lucre ſake? and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:35402:7"/>whether it be not one thouſand ſix hundred years agoe ſince <hi>John</hi> in the <hi>Revelations</hi> ſaid, all the world went out after them, and wondered and ſaid, who was able to make Warre with the Beaſt, which made warre with the Lamb, and ſlew the Saints which kept the teſtimony of Jeſus? Come, anſwer whether you are not of this Church? and whether your weapons be ſuch as proceed out of the mouth of the Lamb, or ſuch as they uſed who made warre with the Lamb, and ſlew, and caſt ſome of the Saints into Priſon?</item>
               <item>VI. If your Church be true, then Anſwer, Where did the Church of Chriſt appoint one, and onely one to ſpeak at a ſet-time, and count it diſorder for any for any to ſpeak beſides him which ſtands in the high place? or whether, if any thing were revealed to another that ſtood by the firſt, ought not to hold his peace? whether this was ever counted confuſion and diſorder, by ſuch who were the true Church, and had the Spirit of God; or by the falſe Church onely, who were gone from the Spirit of the Lord, and to whom Revealations is ceaſed?</item>
               <item>VII. Whether all, who walk not contrary to the Scripture, as ye doe in theſe things, and abide not in the Doctrine of Chriſt, have either the Father, or the Son? and whether ſuch can Miniſter Chriſt, who have him not revealed in themſelves?</item>
               <item>VIII. Whether your Praying, Singing, and Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and all your Ordinances, and Sacrifices be not ſinne? and all your Incenſe, as if you bleſt an Idol, or ſlew a man; and offered ſwines fleſh, which is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bomination to the Lord? and whether ſwines fleſh, and harlots fleſh be not the fame as ever it was?</item>
            </list>
            <p>Come all you people of what ſort or opinion ſoever you be. Come all you Independants, Baptiſts, and, Separatiſts of what Body or Church ſoever, who are not acted, guided, and led by the Pure, Eternall, Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changeable light of Chriſt in your Conſciences, the Church of the Firſt-born, which is in God, you
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:35402:7"/>know not, nor the generall Aſſembly, whoſe Names are written in Heaven ye are not yet come too, but ye are all of the Synagogue of Satan, and the God of the world hath blinded the eye which is the Light, which ſhould lead you to deſcern the Body, which is the Church; and my bowels are yerning, and my love is iſſuing out towards you all; and by the power of the Lord, and in the Maieſty of the Lord I am con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained to deal plainly with you all, and to wound you all, and to heal the hurt of none ſlightly, as your falſe Teachers have long done; who have dau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed with untempered morter, and ſpoken peace to the wicked; who have not wounded the head of the wicked, nor the hairy ſcalpe of ſuch as hath been found in rebellion againſt the Lord; and have laid a foundation, but have not taken away the rubbiſh in which the book of the Law hath been hid, and is hid in you, whom the God of the world hath blinded the eye which ſhould ſee him, who is inviſible, and the true foundation and everlaſting arme which is underneath, upon which all the generation of the Righteous did build; but you are building the New houſe on your Old foundation; and you are garniſhing the Sepulchre of the dead, and you are clothing your ſelves with the white raiment, and ſetting a goodly Miter upon your heads, but the filthy ragges, and rotten ragges, and filthy garment is yet over <hi>Joſhua</hi> the High Prieſt; and he is ſlain, and the world, and the foundations thereof, and the Pillars thereof are ſet upon him; and the great Myſtery hid from you all, which is Chriſt within, the hope of Glory. And you are all in the Darkneſſe, and out of the Light, which makes manifeſt Darkneſſe, and the Light ſhines in the darkneſſe. And you who are in the darkneſſe, by the children of Light are comprehended, and by him which is Judged of no man, nor careth not for mans Judgement, are you all Judged, and Condemned,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:35402:8"/>but the Light your ſelves cannot comprehend who are in the darkneſſe.</p>
            <p>Therefore all come down into the deep, that you may ſee the wonderous workes of the Lord in the great waters; and that ye may be drawn out of the waters, upon which the Whore ſitteth, which waters have gone over, and are over your heads; (read with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, Chriſt the Head of every man) ſtand ſtill awhile, that you may ſee the Salvation of the Lord, and his his power riſe in you, and his arme bring forth Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation for you; and the Sea ſhall be dried up, and the tongue of the <hi>Egyptian</hi> ſhall be ſmitten in the ſeven ſtreams, and the foundations of the World ſhall be diſcovered, and the Channells of the Sea ſhall be ſeene, and he ſhall be known; and what manner of man he is that rebukes the Windes, and the Sea obey him, and the ſwadling Band you ſhall know which binds and ſhuts up the Sea as with doores: and ſaith to the proud, and raging Waves thereof, hitherto ſhalt thou goe, and no further. This is our God whom, we have been looking for; this is the Living which we have been ſeeking amongſt the dead: he it is which was in this place, and we knew it not; we will be gald, and reioyce in his day.</p>
            <p>This is day of the Lords might power, this is the Day of the Lambs Marriage, and the Supper of the great King, and the day of the Lords Controverſie, with all his Enemies which are gathered together with <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog,</hi> as the ſands of the Sea; and are per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuting, impriſoning the Saints, and compaſſing about the beloved City, and the fire of the Lord is coming out of Heaven to deſtroy you all. And the Lyon is come out of the Thicket, and the deſtroyer of the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles is on his way, and the ſword of the Lord is drawne and Made reddy for the ſlaughter, and the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:35402:8"/>ſlain of the Lord ſhall be many, and made drunk with the blood of Bulls, Rams, and Goats. Oh that you would, be wiſe! Oh that you would underſtand this! that you would conſider your latter end! but you are a people voide of Councell; neither is there any underſtanding in you, for ye have reiected the pure, eternall, and immortall Word of the Lord, and behinde your backs ye have caſt it, and you have lightly eſteemed, and counted the Light, which is the rock of Ages, as a low thing; and ye have ſtumbled at the ſtumbling ſtone, and the rock that begets, hath been lightly eſteemed by you, who are wiſe in your own eyes, and prudent in your own conceits; and ye have reiected the Law of the Lord, and the word of love, and what wiſdome is there in you? and the light by you, wherewith Chriſt hath enlightned every man to you who are high in profeſſions, and above the door, it is become fooliſhneſſe, though it be the tryed Stone, the Corner Stone, and the Foundation Stone, and to us that have tryed him, and beleeve in him, he is precious; but to you who are wiſe; as I ſaid before, this is too low a thing for you to tell you of (that) which ſmiteth you in your Conſciences, and checketh you, reproveth you in ſecret: this ſay you, who are in your ſinnes, and pleading for ſinne, and ſaying none can be without ſinne while they live; this ſay you, we knew long ſince. To thee I ſay, whoever thou art; thou kneweſt thy Condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion then; for had not he come a light into the World, thou hadſt had no ſinne: wherefore now thou haſt no cloak for thy ſinne. But I ſay, hadſt thou come down when thou firſt knew this thing, and turned at the reproof of the Lord, when he firſt ſmote thee, and made thee to ſtart, and perſued thee in the hinder parts, when thy heart was Adulterated, and went a whoring from the Lord. I ſay, hadſt thou then come down, and waited in the Light of the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:35402:9"/>Lord which ſmote thee, thou wouldeſt have found, and felt the Power of the Lord, which is the Word of the Lord, ariſen in thee like a fire, and like a hammer, even the word within the Vaile would have deſtroyed the covering which hath been over all Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and rent the Vaile which hath been over all people, and is yet over you; and when the Scriptures you read, with all your Originall, as Hebrew, Greek, and Latine, you cannot underſtand becauſe the Vaile is over your heart; and Chriſt, the hope of Glory is entred within the Vaile, which ſhould condemne ſinne, and finiſh tranſgreſſion, and deſtroy him which hath the power of death, which is the Devill, and bring in everlaſting Righteouſneſſe.</p>
            <p>And this Righteouſneſſe are you ignorant of, and in your owne you are, which is as filthy ragges, and it doth not ſet you free from ſinne, becauſe it is ſinne, and ſo you being all gone out of the way, which is Chriſt within, Gods Righteouſneſſe: you cannot ceaſe from ſinne, and ſo your Prayers are ſinne, and your ſtriving, ſeeking, and knocking is ſinne, becauſe you are ſtriving, and ſeeking amiſſe; and ſo though thou take unto thee water, and waſh thee with never ſo much Sope, yet thine iniquity, and thy Righteouſneſſe is marked, and all one be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lord. Therefore in the bowels of love I Exhort you all, and in the power and dread of the Lord, I warne you all to come down to the manifeſtation of the Spirit of God, and unto the Light of God, and Grace of God, which hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared to all men; and freely given from the Lord, and is the Lords Tallent, and the Lords gift, which is perfect, and pure, as God is pure, and unchange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, and varies not, and is freely given to every man to profit withall.</p>
            <p>I ſay to this, come down, if ever you expect Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation;
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:35402:9"/>feel it, and wait in it, which is meek, and low of heart: for untill this be done, namely, to ſee the Light ſeparated from the darkneſſe, and the Precious from the Vile, you ſhall never be as Gods mouth, and all your Teachers, who are gone from this, are out of Gods Counſell, and ſhall never pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit the people; and all ye Profeſſors, of what Sect ſoever, or of what Opinion ſoever, who are gone from this, you are them, which are not Sonnes of God, being not led by this ſpirit of God, which he hath given to every man to profit withall; and the price is in the hand of the fool, and you are the unprofitable ſervants which hide your Lords Tallent, and muſt be caſt into utter darkneſſe, where the worms dieth not, and the fire goeth not out, but where there is wailing, weeping, and gnaſhing of teeth; and where the Fire of the Lord ſhall conſume and burn for ever, and the Breath of the Lord as a ſtream of Brimſtone, doth blow it up, and kindle it.</p>
            <p>I ſay again to you all, Come downe out of all your owne wiſdome, and own your ſhame, and ſit in the duſt before the Lord: if ſo be there may be but hope, and this is hard for you who are rich, and wiſe, to become fooles for Chriſt, that ye may feel, and know the Spirit of the Lord, which is the Spirit of Truth, from the lying ſpirit, which is of the World, and leads from the Lord into the World, and hides the Seed, to which all the Promiſes are, and vailes the Pure, which is not of this World, nor its Kingdome, Power, nor Glory is not of this World: And this is he which you cannot believe in, who are the friendſhip and love of the world, worſhipping, and honouring, and receiving honour one of another; in him you cannot believe, who receives not honour of men.</p>
            <p>Nevertheleſſe to him you muſt come, and to him you
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:35402:10"/>muſt how; and whoſe Image hath been marred in you, and hath bowed down, and hath been ſlaine ſince the world was ſet in mans heart; and this is the gate, and the door by which the Sheep enter: and this is the Soules Anchor, which anchors up the Immortall Soul to God: And this is the Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herd of the ſheep, and hath laid down his Life for the ſheep, and they hear his Voice, and follow him through great tribulation; and in the Regeneration, they are waſhing their Robes, and making them white in the Bloud of the Lamb. And unleſſe to him you come out of all your own thoughts, reaſonings, and imaginations, and take him for your rule and guide to to walk by, you ſhall never know the peace which is upon the Iſrael of God: And all ye that kindle a fire, and walk in the light of the ſparks which your ſelves have kindled, ye ſhall all lie down in ſorrow, ſaith the Lord God.</p>
            <p>But Peace upon all, and Joy upon all who walke in the light of the Lord, and are led by the Spirit of the Lord, who leadeth out of ſinne and iniquity which ye all lie in, in the way of Righteouſneſſe, Holineſſe, and Purity, which becomes his houſe for evermore. And oh that thou hadſt hearkned into me, ſaith the Lord! then had thy Peace been like a River, and thy Righteouſneſſe like the Waves of the Sea; the Seed, the light to which all the Promiſes are, had been as the Starres in the Firmament; and the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpring of thy Bowels, like the ſands of the Sea-ſhore, innumerable! Oh that you had taken heed to the light which ye call a low thing, I would ſoon have ſubdued your enemies under you, and turned my hand aganſt all them that hated you; he would have fed you alſo with the fineſt of the Wheat, and with honey out of the Rock would he have ſatisfied you! but you would not hearken to my Voice, ſaith the Lord, which ſmore you, and reproved you upon
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:35402:10"/>your beds: ſo the Lord hath given many of you o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to your ſinnes, and over to your hearts luſts, to ſee what you will do in the latter end. And Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome hath uttered her voice in the ſtreets, ſaying, Turne in, for I have mingled my Wine, I have ſlaine my Fatlings, I have furniſhed my Table, and all things are ready, and he hath long ſtood at the door and knockt; and hath long waited upon you all, that he might be gracious; and I am a witneſſe for the Lord againſt you all, that he hath rather deſired your return, than your ruine: and the Lord hath long ſtriven with you, and his compaſſions have been great, and exceeding large towards his dwelling houſe, in ſending to you his Meſſengers, time after time, and day after day: But ye have whiped, ſtoned, impriſoned, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted, them, by whom the Lord would have healed you; but ye have choſen your own wayes, and ye have delighted in that, and lived in that, and been led and taught by that by which the ſoul of the Righteous hath been grieved, and made ſad among you. And what will ye do in the day of the Lords Controverſie, which is near at hand, and coming upon you all as a ſweeping raine, that leaveth no food, and as a mighty tempeſt againſt the World, is the Lord God riſing, and ye ſhall feel his Spirit, which ye have grieved long, ſhall not alwayes ſtrive with you? And though the Lord hath long waited to be mercifull and gracious unto you, I ſay, though he hath been long ſtill, and refrained him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and ye have thought he had been altogether ſuch an one as your ſelves; and becauſe ſentence hath not been ſpeedily executed upon you, and becauſe he hath reſtrained his Anger, and hath not ſtirred up all his Wrath againſt you, who are an Hypocritcall Nation, and Children, in whom there is no truth, which have dealt deceitfully, and treacherouſly with the Lord for all his loving kindneſſe, as treacherous <hi>Judah</hi> did. Yet the Lord will reprove you for all your iniquities, and ſet
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:35402:11"/>them in order before you: even he that hath long time been ſtill, and refrained himſelf, will now ariſe, like a Travelling Woman he will deſtroy, and devour at once; and I am trouble for you all, my Country-men, for there's cauſe of a Lamentation, when I weigh, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider your ſad and wofull eſtate, my heart is trouble for you all, how you have covered your ſelves with the Saints words, Prophets words, Chriſts and the Apoſtles words, but are out of that life<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> purity, and holineſſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> which they lived in, which becomes the houſe of God for evermore. And how ye are clothed, and how your Teachers are clothed; and are like the ſheep, and onely like them, but are inwardly ravened from the light, and Spirit of the Lord, and ſubſtance which they were in, which was Chriſt in them, the hope of Glory: and I am trouble for you all, and my heart is grieved for the place of my Nativity, and I can but ſeek the welfare of all the Iſrael of God that are among you: For which, I am but look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon as to be your enemy, and a diſquieter and trouble of your Iſrael. And how many falſe Teachers, and baſtards, and falſe Profeſſors, and falſe Chriſtians, that have Chriſt only in words, as the Jewes had, which ſlew him, and ſaid, had they lived in the dayes of their Fathers; they would not have ſlaine the Prophets? How many of theſe have riſen up againſt me in this Nation, and in my own Country, like <hi>Sanba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>let</hi> and <hi>Tobiah,</hi> have riſen up a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt me with priſons and ſtones, and the Jewes weapons which Crucified Chriſt, to villifie me, as they did <hi>Nehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miah,</hi> that they might cauſe the work of the Lord to ceaſe? And how do they rage, and do plainly declare, by their perſecution, and are grieved at their very hearts, that there is one left to ſeek the welfare of his Country-men?</p>
            <p>And I lay it upon you all, and in the power of the Lord God I charge you all conſider, and lay it to heart, before it be too late, and hid from your eyes what kind of Miniſters you have, and whether they are Miniſters of the Letter which kils, or of the Spirit that gives life, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.6.
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:35402:11"/>Whether Miniſters of Chriſt, whoſe Weapons were never carnall, as clubs, or priſons; or Miniſters of Antichriſt, whoſe weapons were not ſpiritual, but carnal, as the Popes, and Presbyterians, and their Miniſters weapons are, which are impriſoning, and in all Ages did impriſon, and ſlay the Saints, and ſuch as could not ioyn with the Idolaters, nor worſhip in their Maſſe-houſes, nor Idol Temples, but kept the teſtimony of Jeſus, and the Word of God? And all ye Magiſtrates in the Nation, I charge you all in the Power of the Lord, conſider what you do, and how you do perſecute, or lay the ſword upon them as evill doers, who are moved of the Lord to come to bear a teſtimony againſt all your Idol Temples, Teachers, and their Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip; or to ſpeak a few words unto you in the name and Power of the Lord, to turn you from darkneſs unto light, from the power of Satan unto God. And if you do but read the Scripture which ye ſay is your Rule, you ſhall find, that this was the practice of Chriſt, to go into their Synagouges and Temple, and to preach in the Villages, Streets and Markets, as we do; for which they were counted diſturbers by many, yea, by almoſt all, the chief Prieſts that ſaid they were wiſe, and ſuch as were as learned, and had the Hebrew, Greek and Latine, and had the Scriptures, the Prophets words, as your falſe Teachers, who are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly ravened from the two Original of the Scriptures, which is the Spirit from whence the Scripture did proceed: theſe have Chriſts words, and the Apoſtles words; but are perſecuting us, who are led by the Spirit, which the Sons of God in all Ages, and Chriſt, and his Apoſtles were led by, and we are in the ſame life, and found in the ſame practice, for which we are perſecuted as deceivers, and ſeducers, as they were: and we read, when the Apoſtles came into their Synagouges, the Ruler thereof was not like many of you, who give a charge to your Officers to pull us out; but they ſaid unto them, If ye have any word of Exhortation for the people, ſay on.</p>
            <p>And what is our tranſgreſſion? and what is our ſin? is
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:35402:12"/>it not the ſame which the Apoſtles, and Chriſt was found in, which was to reprove ſinne in the gate, to lay the Axe to the Root? and the ſword of the Spirit did they draw againſt all Hypocrites, painted graves, and ſepulchers, who were inwardly full of all manner of wickedneſſe, as ye are in <hi>Stafford</hi>-ſhire. For which my life doth ſuffer, and bears a teſtimony againſt you all, who have a Name to live, but are dead, and who call your ſelves Jewes, and Chriſtians, but are fill'd with all manner of wickedneſſe, and are out of the Lambs nature, and childes nature, and ſo are of the ſynagouge of Satan; and your Goals, and your Officers houſes, which call themſelves Chriſtians, and us deceivers, wherein you have impriſoned me ten times, not for the breach of any Law of the Nation, but for crying out againſt Drunkeneſſe, and all manner of wickedneſſe, which in theſe Evil doers houſes do abound, which ſhould only, both them and their houſes, be for the puniſhment not of the Righteous, unto whom the Law was not added, but unto the Unrighteous, unto which it was.</p>
            <trailer>The End.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:35402:12"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
